## **RUCHIR BISHT**

## Professional Summary

Sr. Software Engineer with ~ 4 years of experience leading a team of 3-4 engineers, specializing in full-stack development and Al-driven solutions. Currently advancing **Al innovation at BlackNGreen** by developing Smart Virtual Assistants powered by Language Models to enhance user experiences. Previously contributed to the **Citi KYC-Global Project**, delivering/deploying various features. *Proficient in Java with strong object-oriented programming skills, committed to best practices in coding, quality enhancement, module monitoring, logs management, failure handling, and documentation.* 

## **Work History**

#### Sr. Software Engineer | Feb 2024 - Present | Gurugram

#### BlackNGreen Advanced Mobile Solutions Pvt. Ltd. | EVA-Smart Al Assistant

- Engineered advanced AI agents capable of performing diverse roles with human-like conversational abilities, deployed across multiple channels including voice calls, video calls, and text interfaces. Built interactive React.js frontends for real-time chat, AI-driven customer support dashboards, and agent management panels.
- Successfully deployed EVA, a voice assistant, to global enterprises such as Orange, Micoope, MTN, Forza Delivery,
  Africell, Revi, VIVA Bolivia, Digicel, Claro, and many more. Designed control center that allows enterprises to configure
  Al assistant behaviors, view analytics, and monitor interactions in real time.
- Integrated DeepGram and Azure speech models with LLMs to enhance conversational capabilities, employing
  mechanisms like chunking, filler audios, and voice utterance timeouts to reduce average response time from 7
  seconds to 2.5 seconds.
- Implemented conversational analysis features such as sentiment analysis, statement and overall emotion detection, achieving a customer satisfaction (CSAT) score of 94%.
- Developed and optimized multi-threading logic for event communication via WebRTC and socket connections, ensuring proper thread state management and sequence integrity.

# Digital Specialist Engineer | Aug 2021 - Feb 2024 | Chandigarh Infosys Ltd. | Citi KYC-Global Project

- Designed and implemented pivotal features, including KYC Case Review, Extension on KYC WI, etc. Executed multiple Proof of Concepts to discern the most feasible design solutions.
- Delivered multiple solutions in various sprints with decrease in Application defects rate to 29%.
- Developed APIs to add functionality to the application and ensure their seamless integration into the larger application architecture for CITI client.
- Migrated the legacy frontend application from significantly reducing rendering time and Google Web ToolKit (GWT)
  to Angular, enhancing overall performance by applying the concepts of Lazy Loading, Http Interceptors, Guard
  Routing & Module Federation.
- Developed APIs to add functionality to the application and ensure their seamless integration into the larger
  application architecture for CITI client. Actively used Sonarlint to detect and resolve over 350+ code issues and
  conflicts, resulting in a substantial improvement in code quality.

## **☆** Skills

- Java, J2EE, Spring Boot, Hibernate (JPA)
- Websockets | Webrtc
- ReactJS-Redux | AngularJS
- Kafka, Kibana, Logstash,
- Version Control Git | Github | GitLab

- Prometheus | Grafana
- MySql | MongoDB | Elasticsearch | Redis
- Issue tracking tools JIRA | Asana | Confluence
- Docker | Jenkins
- Code Quality SonarQube

## **Education**

Bachelor in Technology in Computer Science (2017–2021)
Guru Gobind Singh Indraprastha University, Delhi – **CGPA – 8.9**